<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" ?>
<casaxml xmlns="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/psetTypes.html"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/casa.xsd
    file:///opt/casa/code/xmlcasa/xml/casa.xsd">

    <task type="function" name="pieflag" category="analysis">
        <shortdescription>Flags bad data by comparing with clean channels in bandpass-calibrated data.</shortdescription>
        <description>
                
                Let's face it, flagging is laborious and boring.
                
                You want a simple and effective tool to fight rfi.
                
                pieflag does not attempt the overly complex task of
                ingesting raw un-flagged data in the hope of producing
                clean output with no further required manual inspection.
                
                Instead, pieflag operates on a much simpler philosophy:
                you need to do some very basic pre-processing of your
                data so that pieflag can do its job robustly using a
                minimal set of assumptions.
                
                While the amount of documentation below may seem
                counter to the above pledge of simplicity, don't worry,
                the content is quite straight-forward. You should read
                it in full before using pieflag.
		
		
		
                pieflag works by comparing visibility amplitudes in
                each frequency channel to a 'reference' channel that
                is rfi-free, or manually ensured to be rfi-free.
                pieflag performs this comparison independently for
                each correlation on each baseline, but will flag all
                correlations if threshold conditions are met. To
                operate effectively, pieflag must be supplied with
                bandpass-calibrated data; preliminary gain-
		calibration is also preferable (more details below).
                
                pieflag has two core modes of operation -- static and
                dynamic flagging -- with an additional extend mode.
                Which mode you choose is largely dictated by the
                type of data you have. Instructions for
		pre-processing your data and selecting the best
                mode of operation are provided further below.
                
                Once you have carried out your pre-processing and
                selected the mode of operation, pieflag should work
                well 'out of the box' with its default parameters.
		By comparing to a clean reference channel,
		essentially all bad data will be identified and
		flagged by pieflag.
                
		
		
                One reference channel is needed per spectral window.
                The choice of reference channel is important:
                whenever the reference channel is unavailable on
                a given baseline, pieflag will flag all channels on
                that baseline in the spectral window.
                
                If your data exhibits a non-flat spectrum in the
                log10(amp) vs log10(freq) plane, pieflag can fit
		and account for a power law or curved power law per
		correlation per baseline. pieflag can also account
		for sensitivity variations across your band by
		taking into account the system equivalent flux
		density (SEFD) or other similar measure of relative
		sensitivity.
                
		
		
		Modes of operation:
                
                - DYNAMIC mode flagging:
                   If you expect the amplitude on a baseline to
		   vary significantly with time, for example due
		   to source structure or atmospheric noise, then
		   choose this mode. Dynamic flagging works by
		   slicing your data into time chunks. 'chunktime'
		   should be specified to ensure that the
		   amplitudes on all baseline remain approximately
		   constant within the time chunk. For each
		   correlation on each baseline, this mode will
		   begin by calculating the median and standard
		   deviation of the reference channel for each
		   time chunk. It will then go through each
		   baseline, channel, and correlation for each
		   time chunk and compare the median and standard
		   deviation to the reference channel values
		   (after accounting for spectral fit and SEFD,
		   if requested; the former will be performed on
		   a per-chunk basis). If the standard deviation
		   exceeds 'stdmax' times the reference channel
		   value, or if the median exceeds 'maxoffset'
		   times the observed standard deviation away from
		   the reference channel median, then the chunk will
		   be flagged. This is a pseudo-rms, separating the
		   offset from the data spread. pieflag avoids using
		   true rms values here to enable efficient flagging
		   on baselines exhibiting structure (i.e. not just
		   a smooth spectrum as a function of frequency).
		   In this way, for structured fields, flagging can
		   be made more sensitive to changes in standard
		   deviation than to changes in overall offset
		   (ultimately, large values of the latter will
		   indicate spurious data). Set 'maxoffset' by first
		   checking amp vs freq for a single baseline.
		
                - STATIC mode flagging:
                   If the criteria above for dynamic flagging do
		   not apply, for example you are looking at an
		   unresolved calibrator or a sparse field, then
		   choose this mode. Static mode will begin by
		   calculating the median amplitude and median
		   absolute deviation (MAD) of amplitudes for
                   each baseline and correlation on the reference
                   channel. It will then go through each correlation
                   for each channel on each baseline and assign a
                   'badness' value of 1 to each visibility that has
                   an amplitude that deviates from the reference
                   channel's median by more that 'madmax' times the
                   reference channel's MAD (after accounting for
                   spectral fit and SEFD, if requested). It will
                   assign a badness value of 2 if the visibility has
                   amplitude greater than 2*madmax*MAD. This mode
                   will then split up your data into bins containing
                   'binsamples' integration dump timescales. If the
		   sum of badness values exceeds 1 then the bin is
		   flagged. To illustrate, the idea here is that a
		   badness value of 1 with default madmax=6
		   corresponds to a 4-sigma outlier. The odds of
		   having two 4-sigma outliers within binsamples=5
		   samples is equivalent to a discrete 5.6-sigma
		   event (binomial statistics).
                
                - EXTEND mode flagging:
                   For each baseline and channel, this mode will apply
		   a sliding time window (independently within each
		   scan) to examine each correlation. If the fraction
		   of data flagged (by pieflag) within the window
		   exceeds a threshold, the whole window will be
		   flagged. This is useful for flagging periods of bad
		   data that may be below the thresholds for static
		   or dynamic flagging, but which are adjacent to bad
		   data clearly identified by these modes.
		
		
		
		Let's run through the steps needed to pieflag your data.
                First, gather the following ingredients:
                
                1. Manually flag your bandpass calibrator. This shouldn't
                   take you very long, and it's good to get acquainted with
                   your data.
                
                2. For each spectral window of your target data, identify
		   a clean 'reference' channel that is rfi-free. If all
		   channels are affected by rfi, then pick the cleanest one
		   and manually flag all offending data on this channel only.
                
                3. Bandpass calibrate your data. Use the clean reference
		   channel in each spectral window to calibrate gains,
		   so that amplitude fluctuations due to the atmosphere
		   are largely removed. There is no strong need to
		   bootstrap the flux density scale from a standard
		   calibrator. If this is performed, ensure that gain
		   solutions are not derived using rfi-affected channels.
                
		4. Apply your calibration solutions to the data. pieflag
		   will perform all analysis using the 'CORRECTED_DATA'
		   column of your measurement set.
		
                5. Plot amplitude versus frequency for your data. Check
		   that the spectrum has not been artificially normalized
		   by the 'solnorm' parameter (should be false for
		   bandpass calibration and true for secondary gain
		   calibration). Estimate the polynomial order in the
		   log10(amp)-log10(freq) plane. 0th order is flat
		   (independent of frequency), 1st order is a power law,
		   2nd order is a curved power law.
                
                6. If appropriate, obtain an SEFD curve for your band.
                   This will be used to scale the sensitivity for each
                   channel relative to the reference channel in that spw.
                   For narrow spectral windows this may not be required.
                   For Jansky VLA data between 0.28-0.48 and 1-50 GHz,
                   SEFD curves are provided as part of the download
                   package for pieflag (but without quality assurance;
                   see more details under the keyword argument help).
                
                
		
                And now for pieflag's delicious recipe:
                
                7. Decide whether you want static or dynamic flagging.
                   See descriptions of these modes above. The default
                   parameter values should work well with all data.
                
                8. Decide if you want to extend the static or dynamic
                   flags (hint: probably). See description of this mode
                   above. The default parameter values should work well.
                
                9. Press go, then have a slice of pie. The end result
                   should not require any additional manual flagging.
                
                
		
                Assumptions:
                 * Lock files are unimportant; pieflag will remove them.
                 * Existing flags are backed up, either from a previous
                   task (e.g. applycal) or using flagmanager (mode=save).
                   pieflag will not create a backup prior to operation.
                 * All selected spw's have the same number of channels.
                 * The integration time for your spw's doesn't change.
                 * pieflag doesn't need to flag your reference channels
                 * For a given baseline, if the reference channel for a
                   correlation is missing (e.g. due to online flags),
                   then all correlations on all other channels in the
                   spw will be flagged.
                 * If one correlation requires flagging in static,
                   dynamic, or extend mode, all will be flagged.
                 * Scans do not have multiple subscans. If they do,
                   then pieflag will only operate on subscan 0.
                
                
		
                Limitations:
                * pieflag is not suitable for spectral line experiments
                  when the observed lines are strong. However, pieflag is
                  appropriate for spectral line experiments when channels
                  are dominated by receiver noise.
		* If you are performing dynamic flagging on a target with
		  significant structure, the accuracy of spectral fitting
		  may be degraded. Increase maxoffset to compensate.
                
		
                
                Detailed descriptions of keyword arguments are provided
                at the end of this help file.
                
		
                
                Pieflag originally written by Enno Middelberg 2005-2006.
                Reference: E. Middelberg, 2006, PASA, 23, 64
                http://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0603216
                
                Rewritten for use in CASA and updated to account for
                wideband and SEFD effects by Christopher A. Hales 2014.
                                
                Version 3.0
                Tested with CASA Version 4.3.0 using Jansky VLA data
                27 March 2015
                
                Thanks to Kumar Golap, Justo Gonzalez, Jeff Kern,
                Urvashi Rau, Sanjay Bhatnagar, and of course Enno Middelberg
                for expert advice. Thanks to Emmanuel Momjian for providing
                Jansky VLA SEFD data for L and X bands (EVLA Memos 152 and
                166) and to Bryan Butler for providing access to all other
                bands from the Jansky VLA Exposure Calculator.
                
                Code available at: http://github.com/chrishales/pieflag
                pieflag is released under a BSD 3-Clause Licence; refer to
		the header in task_pieflag.py for details.
		Reference: C. A. Hales, E. Middelberg, 2014, Astrophysics
		Source Code Library, 1408.014
	        http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2014ascl.soft08014H
                
                If you use pieflag we would appreciate your acknowledgement
                by citing Enno's PASA paper and Chris' ASCL entry (see above).
                
                
        </description>

        <input>
            <param type="string" name="vis" mustexist="true">
                <description>input MS</description>
                <value />
            </param>
            <param type="int" name="field">
                <description>field index number (e.g. 0)</description>
                <value>0</value>
            </param>
            <param type="string" name="refchanfile" mustexist="true">
                <description>file where reference channel per spw is defined</description>
                <value />
            </param>
            <param type="int" name="fitorder_RR_LL">
                <description>order of RR/LL spectral fitting (0/1/2)</description>
                <value>1</value>
                <allowed kind="enum">
                    <value>0</value>
                    <value>1</value>
                    <value>2</value>
                </allowed>
            </param>
            <param type="int" name="fitorder_RL_LR">
                <description>order of RL/LR spectral fitting (0/1/2)</description>
                <value>0</value>
                <allowed kind="enum">
                    <value>0</value>
                    <value>1</value>
                    <value>2</value>
                </allowed>
            </param>

            <param type="bool" name="scalethresh">
                <description>scale thresholds across band (e.g. using SEFD)</description>
                <value>False</value>
            </param>
            <param type="string" name="SEFDfile" subparam="true">
                <description>file containing SEFD vs frequency</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
                <value>dummytext</value>
            </param>
            <param type="bool" name="plotSEFD" subparam="true">
                <description>plot relative sensitivity assumed across band</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
                <value>False</value>
            </param>

            <param type="bool" name="dynamicflag">
                <description>dynamic mode flagging</description>
                <value>False</value>
            </param>
            <param type="double" name="chunktime" subparam="true">
                <description>chunk time (seconds)</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
                <value>300.0</value>
            </param>
            <param type="double" name="stdmax" subparam="true">
                <description>standard deviation threshold to flag chunktime</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
		<value>2.0</value>
            </param>
            <param type="double" name="maxoffset" subparam="true">
                <description>offset threshold in standard deviations (danger!)</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
		<value>50.0</value>
            </param>

            <param type="bool" name="staticflag">
                <description>static mode flagging</description>
                <value>False</value>
            </param>
            <param type="double" name="madmax" subparam="true">
                <description>MAD threshold for assigning badness to a visibility</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
		<value>6.0</value>
            </param>
            <param type="int" name="binsamples" subparam="true">
                <description>successive integrations to search for outliers</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
		<value>5</value>
            </param>

            <param type="bool" name="extendflag">
                <description>extend mode flagging</description>
                <value>False</value>
            </param>
            <param type="double" name="boxtime" subparam="true">
                <description>sliding boxcar width (seconds)</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
                <value>300.0</value>
            </param>
            <param type="double" name="boxthresh" subparam="true">
                <description>flag boxtime if flagged fraction exceeds boxthresh (%)</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
		<value>10.0</value>
            </param>

            <param type="bool" name="mycluster">
                <description>user defined cluster for parallelism? (False=automatic)</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
                <value>False</value>
            </param>
            <param type="int" name="numthreads" subparam="true">
                <description>number of threads on local host (0=90% CPU, 1=serial)</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
		<value>0</value>
            </param>
            <param type="string" name="configfile" subparam="true">
                <description>name of file containing cluster details</description>
                <!-- dummy value, see constraints section below for default value -->
                <value>default</value>
            </param>


            <constraints>
               <when param="scalethresh">
                    <equals type="bool" value="False"></equals>
                    <equals type="bool" value="True">
                        <default param="SEFDfile"><value type="string" mustexist="true"></value></default>
                        <default param="plotSEFD"><value type="bool">False</value></default>
                    </equals>
               </when>

               <when param="dynamicflag">
                    <equals type="bool" value="False"></equals>
                    <equals type="bool" value="True">
                        <default param="chunktime"><value type="double">300.0</value></default>
                        <default param="stdmax"><value type="double">2.0</value></default>
                        <default param="maxoffset"><value type="double">50.0</value></default>
                    </equals>
               </when>

               <when param="staticflag">
                    <equals type="bool" value="False"></equals>
                    <equals type="bool" value="True">
                        <default param="madmax"><value type="double">6.0</value></default>
                        <default param="binsamples"><value type="int">5</value></default>
                    </equals>
               </when>

               <when param="extendflag">
                    <equals type="bool" value="False"></equals>
                    <equals type="bool" value="True">
                        <default param="boxtime"><value type="double">300.0</value></default>
                        <default param="boxthresh"><value type="double">10.0</value></default>
                    </equals>
               </when>
		
               <when param="mycluster">
                    <equals type="bool" value="False">
                        <default param="numthreads"><value type="int">1</value></default>
                    </equals>
                    <equals type="bool" value="True">
                        <default param="configfile"><value type="string" mustexist="true">pieflag_cluster-config.txt</value></default>
                    </equals>
               </when>
            </constraints>
        </input>

        <returns type="void"/>
        <example>

----- Detailed descriptions of keyword arguments -----

   
   Keyword arguments:
       
       
       vis -- Name of input measurement set containing bandpass-calibrated
              data in the 'CORRECTED_DATA' column.
       
       
       field -- Field index number (integer). pieflag can only operate on a
                single field at a time.
       
       
       refchanfile -- Name of file where the reference channel per spectral
                      window is defined. Only the spectral windows included
                      in this file will be processed. The format is a bit
                      quirky. The following is a verbatim example of the
                      single line entry required in "sample_refchan.txt" to
                      select reference channels 7, 34, and 10 in spectral
                      windows 0, 4, and 5, respectively:
                      
                      {"0":7,"4":34,"5":10}
       
       
       fitorder_RR_LL -- Polynomial order of the spectral fitting for the
                         RR and LL correlations, using the formula
                         
                         log10(visibility amplitude) = a_o
                                                     + a_1*log10(frequency)
                                                     + a_2*(log10(frequency))**2
                         
                         For order N the fit is performed up to coefficient a_N
                         using the reference channel data independently for
                         each correlation on each baseline. Currently supports
                         orders 0 (frequency independent), 1 (power law), and
                         2 (curved power law). It falls back to a lower fitorder
                         when there are not enough spectral windows to fit the
                         requested order (this will be reported to you if it
                         takes place).
       
       
       fitorder_RL_LR -- Same as above but for correlations RL and LR.
       
       
       scalethresh  -- If true, madmax and stdmax will be scaled across your
                       band according to SEFDfile.
       
         * SEFDfile -- File containing a measure of the relative sensitivity
                       across the channels in your band, for example the
                       system equivalent flux density (SEFD). The input file
                       should contain two columns with a space between them
                       (i.e. no characters such as commas). The two columns
                       are: frequency in Hertz and SEFD in arbitrary units.
                       The data needs to span the frequency range of the
                       channels in your selected spectral windows. pieflag
                       will linearly interpolate the data in SEFDfile to
                       get the relative sensitivity levels at your channel
                       frequencies.
                       
                       For the Jansky VLA, the SEFD from 0.28-0.48, 1-50 GHz
                       is provided as part of the download package for pieflag.
                       This data is provided without any quality assurance!
                       (As Rick Perley would say, if you want an accurate
                       SEFD for your band, or anything for that matter, then
                       measure it yourself.) For L and X bands, the data were
		       obtained from EVLA Memos 152 and 166, respectively.
		       For all other bands, the data were extracted from the
		       Exposure Calculator on 21 August 2014. eg, see
		       https://science.nrao.edu/facilities/vla/docs/manuals
                              /oss/performance/sensitivity
                       Note that for Jansky VLA data observed in 8-bit mode,
                       subband 0 exhibits features that are not captured in
                       the SEFD data provided with pieflag. See EVLA Memo 154
                       for more details. This effect refers to subband 0 as
                       defined in the OPT, which does not necessarily
                       correspond to spectral window 0 in a measurement set.
           
         * plotSEFD -- If True, a plot will be produced showing the relative
                       sensitivity assumed by pieflag across your band.
       
       
       dynamicflag   -- If true, dynamic mode flagging will be performed.
       
         * chunktime -- Length of time chunk (seconds) in which to compare
                        statistics to reference channel.
         
         * stdmax    -- If the standard deviation for a correlation in a chunk
                        of data on a given channel and baseline exceeds stdmax
			times the standard deviation on the reference channel
			(after accounting for SEFD, if requested), then all
			correlations on that channel and baseline in that time
			chunk will be flagged.
	 
	 * maxoffset -- If the median for a correlation in a chunk of data
	                on a given channel and baseline is more than maxoffset
			times the channel's standard deviation away from the
			median of the reference channel (after accounting for
			spectral fit, if requested), then all correlations on
			that channel and baseline in that time chunk will be
			flagged.
       
       
       staticflag     -- If true, static mode flagging will be performed.
       
         * madmax     -- If the amplitude for a visibility on a given
                         correlation, channel, and baseline deviates by
                         more than madmax times the reference channel's
			 MAD away from the reference channel's median
			 (after accounting for spectral fit and SEFD,
			 if requested), assign it a badness value of 1.
			 If the amplitude is twice as deviant as this,
			 assign badness value 2.
         
         * binsamples -- Number of integrations (dump times) to bin
                         when searching for excessive outliers.
       
       
       extendflag    -- If true, extend mode flagging will be performed.
       
         * boxtime   -- Width (seconds) of the sliding boxcar in which
                        to calculate the fraction of flagged visibilities
                        for a given correlation, channel, and baseline.
                        boxtime is limited to individual scans; it does
                        not extend over scan boundaries.
         
         * boxthresh -- Threshold, given as a percentage (not fraction)
                        of flagged visibilities in boxtime beyond which
                        the entire boxcar will be flagged on all
                        correlations for that channel and baseline.
       
       
       mycluster -- If true, specify a custom cluster file for parallel
                    processing. If False, pieflag will set up a default
                    cluster using numthreads on your local host.
                    
                    NOTE: The current version of pieflag makes use of CASA's
                          parallel framework. However, the task 'partition'
                          cannot currently partition baselines. Until this
                          becomes available, pieflag will create copies of
                          your MS for each thread to operate on and remove
                          them when done. pieflag will not check if you have
                          enough disk space to do this.
         
         * numthreads  -- Number of threads (integer) for parallel
                          processing on your local host. For N=0, pieflag
                          will utilize as many threads as possible up to
                          90% of idle CPU capacity. For N>0, pieflag will
                          create N-1 copies of your MS. Performance will
                          degrade if N parallel threads cannot be
                          accommodated by your system (/proc/cpuinfo).
         
         * configfile  -- Name of file containing custom cluster configuration.
                          See CASA's simple_cluster helpfile for examples.
       
       
        </example>
    </task>
</casaxml>
